Finding Aid for William D. Ratcliff papers
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
William D. Ratcliff papers 1962-2004, 1970-1999
Ratcliff, William D.
8 linear feet
2008164 Aa 2
William D. Ratcliff (1941-) was an educator within the Ann Arbor, Mich. Public School system for over 30 years who took an active interest in the education of African-American youth in the Ann Arbor school district. This collection covers the time Ratcliff spent as the Executive Director of the Saturday Academy for African American Students, as well as his time as a guidance counselor within Ann Arbor Public Schools. The collection includes general information about the Ann Arbor Public School district, and information regarding the many organizations and programs that Ratcliff took part in.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was donated by William Ratcliff (donor number 10083 ) in multiple accessions beginning in 2008.
No additions to the records expected.
The record group is open to research.
William D. Ratcliff (1941-) was an educator in the Ann Arbor Public School system for over 30 years, spending his career counseling middle school students. In that time, Ratcliff did much to promote the academic success of African-American students in the Ann Arbor Public School district. His crowning achievement was the creation of the Saturday Academy of African American Students.
The Saturday Academy of African American Students was established in 1990 in response to alarming statistics indicating that a large number of African American students in Ann Arbor Public Schools chose not to take college preparatory mathematics and science courses. Moreover, African American students enrolled in core courses achieved much lower scores than their non-African American peers. Determined to reverse these findings, Ratcliff, along with parents, educators, and the Ann Arbor community, developed the Saturday Academy aimed at raising the number of youth prepared to enter and succeed in core, college preparatory mathematics and science classes at the high school level.
The Saturday Academy enrolled sixth, seventh, and eighth grade students primarily from Washtenaw County. Each week, the Saturday Academy provided students with academic instruction, enrichment, and personal and interpersonal skills. Additionally, viewing parental involvement as key to a student's success, the Saturday Academy instituted parent workshops, which encouraged parents to become actively involved in their children's academic careers. More than a supplementary preparatory program, the Saturday Academy established itself as an enriching learning environment in which African American students identified themselves as high achievers who strive for positive personal development. The non-profit organization received financial support from a variety of contributors including the Ann Arbor Public Schools, Eastern Michigan University, the University of Michigan's NASA Space Grant Program, the Ford Motor Company, and many more.
In addition to his work with the Saturday Academy, Ratcliff is a veteran and served as the president of the Ann Arbor/Ypsilanti chapter of the National Black Child Development Institute, was active in union organizations, and served on numerous school and community committees. Ratcliff retired from the Ann Arbor Public School system in 2004.
William D. Ratcliff (1941-) was a counselor within the Ann Arbor Public School system for over 30 years. This collection documents his time within Ann Arbor Public Schools, as well as his work promoting the achievement of African-American youth in the Ann Arbor educational system. The collection is of value to those interested in collections reflecting community efforts to relieve educational disparities seen among minority students and for documentation on how a successful non-profit organization functions. The collection is divided into six series: the Saturday Academy series (divided into 2 subseries, Administrative and Academics), the African-American and Minority Organizations/Programs series, the Educational Organizations/Programs series, the Ann Arbor Public Schools series, the Newspaper Clippings series, and the Audiovisual materials series.
Subjects:
Ratcliff, William D.; Achievement motivation in adolescence--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; African American students--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; African American teachers--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; African American teachers and the community--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Ann Arbor Public Schools.; National Black Child Development Institute.; Public schools--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Saturday Academy for African American Students.; Photographs.
Subjects - Sound Recordings:
Institutional videos.; National Black Child Development Institute.; Saturday Academy for African American Students.
Genre Terms:
Audiocassettes.; Videotapes.
- Saturday Academy
  The Saturday Academy series (2 linear feet, 1983-2003) is divided into two subseries: Administrative and Academic.
  - Administrative
    The Administrative subseries documents the Saturday Academy's history, organizational structure, program offerings, accomplishments, expenses and contributions. The series contains progress and budget reports, board minutes, and correspondence and the administrative binder of executive director William Ratcliff, which documents the Academy's activities and day-to-day affairs.
    - Background 1990-1995, 5 folders (Box 1)
    - Board meetings and minutes 1992-1995, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Finances 1993-1997, 5 folders (Box 1)
    - Memorandums/correspondences 1986-2003 (Box 1)
    - Reports 1991-1995, 5 folders (Box 1)
    - Session announcements and schedules 1992-1996 (Box 1)
    - William Ratcliff's administrative binder 1992-1995, 4 folders (Box 1)
  - Academics
    The Academics subseries reflects the educational activities and events of the Saturday Academy. The series includes newspaper clippings, newsletters, photographs, program evaluations and proposals, flyers, and material related to the Saturday Academy's Tutoring Program.
    - Book lists 1993-1996 (Box 2)
    - Carpenter After School Academy 1996-1997 (Box 2)
    - Cedar Point Physics Day 1990-1992 (Box 2)
    - Clippings 1991-1999 (Box 2)
    - Events 1991-1997, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Exhibit poster images/photographs
      - Drama workshop, African American Heroes circa 1985-1986 (Box 2)
      - Math undated (Box 2)
      - Mrs. Oliver's Class circa 1983-1984 (Box 2)
      - Negatives 1983 (Box 2)
      - Science (photos by Tina Oliver) circa 1983-1984 (Box 2)
      - Writing undated (Box 2)
    - Future City Competition 1993-1997, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Newsletters 1992-1995 (Box 2)
    - Photographs
      - Academic banquet and other 1992 (Box 2)
      - Future City Competition 1995, 1997 (Box 2)
      - Student assembly 1993 (Box 2)
      - Summer Academy 1993 (Box 2)
    - Program evaluations 1993-1996, 5 folders (Box 2)
    - Proposals undated (Box 2)
    - Saturday Academy for Scarlett Middle School 1990-1997 (Box 2)
    - Staff's report 1991-1993, 4 folders (Box 2)
    - Student assessments undated (Box 2)
    - Student learning tools 1989-1992, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Student work 1992-1994 with undated (Box 2)
    - Tutoring Program 1995 (Box 2)
- African-American and Minority Organizations/Programs
  The African-American and Minority Organizations/Programs series (1.5 linear feet, 1963-2001) includes material related to different committees or organizations William Ratcliff was associated with whose primary concerns were African-American and minority affairs within Ann Arbor and the state of Michigan. The series consists of meeting agendas and minutes, handwritten notes taken by Ratcliff, correspondences, photographs, memorandums, newsletters, reports, and program information regarding programs run by these organizations that Ratcliff was a part of.
  - African-American baseline essays undated, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - African American Male Mentoring Group 1989-1990 (Box 3)
  - Assorted minority programs 1967-1998 (Box 3)
  - Black Curriculum Commission/Human Relations Office 1971-1972, 4 folders (Box 3)
  - Black Educators Association/Black Employee Association, 1971-2001, 4 folders (Box 3)
    (scattered)
  - Black Student Unions of Ann Arbor 1972-1999, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Black Support Group 1985-2001, 3 folders (Box 3)
  - Child and Family Service Task Force on Service to the Poor 1970-1971 (Box 3)
  - Efficacy Detroit 1971-1972, 1986-1987, 2 volumes; 1 folders (Box 3)
  - Handwritten notes 1972-1997, 3 folders (Box 3)
  - Institute for the Growth and Development of African American Students 1989-1992 (Box 4)
  - King/Chavez/Parks Club 1987-1998 (Box 4)
  - Papers regarding race, gender, and schooling in Michigan 1974-1993 (Box 4)
  - NAACP 1984-1997 (Box 4)
  - National African American Parent Involvement Day 1995-1998 (Box 4)
  - National African American Parental Involvement Conference 1997-1998 (Box 4)
  - National Black Child Development Institute 1983-1998, 5 folders (Box 4)
  - National Strategic Action Plan for African-American Males Community Expert Panel 1995 (Box 4)
  - Photographs, African-American Male Mentoring Group 1988-1990 (Box 4)
  - State Minority Affairs 1963, 1970-1971, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Third World Educators' Leadership Workshop 1974 (Box 4)
- Educational Organizations/Programs
  The Educational Organizations/Programs series (0.5 linear feet, 1962-2004) includes material related to different committees or organizations William Ratcliff was associated with whose primary concern was with education in the city of Ann Arbor and the state of Michigan. The series consists of meeting agendas and minutes, correspondences, memorandums, photographs, newsletters, reports, program information regarding programs run by these organizations, presentations given, and certificates received by Ratcliff as a part of these organizations.
  - Ann Arbor Model Cities Program 1971 (Box 4)
  - Cadet Training Program 1974-1975 (Box 4)
  - Certificates 1989-2002 (Box 4)
  - Michigan Education Association 1973-1974, 1986 (Box 4)
  - Michigan Educators' Public Affairs Council 1973-1974 (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous newsletters 1988-2000 (Box 4)
  - Photographs
    - Photos of Ratcliff undated with 1962, 1971 (Box 4)
    - Photos of Ratcliff, American Cancer Society Great American Lock Up undated (Box 4)
    - Ratcliff's Retirement 2004 (Box 4)
    - SAT/ACT workshop 1987-1988 (Box 4)
  - Presentations undated with 1993-1994 (Box 4)
  - Ratcliff's papers/writings undated with 1973 (Box 4)
  - SAT/ACT workshop 1986, 1988, 2 volumes (Box 4)
- Ann Arbor Public Schools
  The Ann Arbor Public Schools series (2 linear feet, 1968-2004) documents information regarding the Ann Arbor Public Schools system. This series includes research/data, studies, reports, committee meeting minutes and agendas, newsletters, photographs, information about specific schools within the Ann Arbor Public Schools system (Slauson Junior High School, Clague Middle School, Pioneer High School, Huron High School, Tappan Middle School, Community High School), correspondences, memorandums, and papers from Ratcliff's time as a guidance counselor.
  - Ann Arbor Public Schools administrative records 1968-2004, 8 folders (Box 5)
  - Ann Arbor Schools Study 1974 (Box 5)
  - Citizens Advisory Committee for School Millage 1973-1974 (Box 5)
  - Citizens Advisory Committee on School Building and Site Needs 1974-1976 (Box 5)
  - Citizens Advisory Committee on School Enrollment and Growth 1973-1974 (Box 5)
  - Clague Middle School undated (Box 5)
  - Community High School undated with 1972 (Box 5)
  - Data and research 1971-2003, 3 folders (Box 5)
  - District Drummers 1992-1998 (Box 5)
  - Effective Schools Project 1981 (Box 6)
  - Guidance counselor papers 1971-2003, 1 volumes; 3 folders (Box 6)
  - Huron High School 1986-1996 (Box 6)
  - Know Your Schools 1969 (Box 6)
  - Master agreements 1970-1978, 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Memorandums 1971-2003, 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Photographs
    - Engineering Club Banquet at Tappan Junior High 1990 (Box 6)
    - Student retreat undated (Box 6)
  - Pioneer High School 1988 (Box 6)
  - Professional Development Task Force 1999-2000 (Box 6)
  - Ratcliff AAPS correspondence 1971-2003 (Box 6)
  - Ratcliff correspondence with superintendents 1971-1992 (Box 6)
  - School board newsletters 1970-1971, 1995 (Box 6)
  - Slauson Junior High School, 1976-1997 (Box 6)
    (with gaps)
  - Special Needs Committee 1970-1972, 3 folders (Box 6)
  - Superintendent's Committee on African-American Achievement Initiatives 1997-1998, 1 volumes; 1 folders (Box 6)
  - Tappan Middle School 1982-1994 (Box 6)
- Newspaper Clippings
  The Newspaper Clippings series (1 linear foot, 1970s-1990s) contains newspapers and newspaper clippings that Ratcliff saved. The majority of the clippings come from The Ann Arbor News and The Detroit Free Press and are related to the topics of race and education. Some interesting topics include the topics of busing and desegregation in Ann Arbor as well as teacher strikes within the Ann Arbor Public Schools system. The clippings are divided into folders by decades. Also included in this series is a collection of the newspaper Muhammad Speaks from the years 1973-1974.
  - Clippings 1970s, 7 folders (Box 7)
  - Clippings 1980s (Box 7)
  - Clippings 1990s (Box 7)
  - Muhammad Speaks 1973-1974, 4 folders (Box 7)
- Audiovisual materials
  The Audiovisual materials series (1 linear foot, 1990-1994 with undated) contains various videotapes relating to the Saturday Academy, the National Black Child Development Institute, topics relating to race and education, William Ratcliff, the Future Cities Competition and Physics day at Cedar Point as well as other programs, videos used in instruction at the Saturday Academy, as well as audiocassettes distributed by the National Black Child Development Institute.
  - VHS videotapes (Box 8)
    - Academy presentation-Your significance and importance in rearing students undated (Box 8)
    - African-Americans as role models for parents and students 1992 (Box 8)
    - Amusement Park Physics misc. 1991 (Box 8)
    - Amusement Parks Physics undated (Box 8)
    - Ann Arbor Middle School Math/Science Academy 1990 (Box 8)
    - Bill Ratcliff undated (Box 8)
    - Delta Sigma Theta sorority and Alpha Phi Alpha fraternity "Reach for the Stars" 1994 (Box 8)
    - Future Cities-Detroit undated (Box 8)
    - Future Cities Engineering Competition 1994 (Box 8)
    - How to say no without losing your friends undated (Box 8)
    - Moving On: Transition from Elementary to Middle School undated (Box 8)
    - NBCDI, Educational Equity for Black Girls, preparing black girls to enter the labor force-Beverly Payne Draper undated (Box 8)
    - NBCDI, Educational Equity for Black Girls, what's happening in educational materials for children undated (Box 8)
    - NBCDI, writing, drama, video undated (Box 8)
    - Ratcliff Original undated (Box 8)
    - Saturday Academy 1992 (Box 8)
    - Saturday Academy undated (Box 8)
    - Saturday Academy banquet 1991 (Box 8)
    - SETT (Self Expression Teen Theatre), The Academy for African American Students undated (2) (Box 8)
    - Summer Academy on CNN 1992 (Box 8)
  - Audiocassette tapes
    - NBCDI audiocassette tapes undated (5) (Box 8)